我希望你會發生的苦惡
人們的高期望都很低的穩定
大利是不像智慧的
大利是由性格
性格不是由職人類的
是由人類的
這可能是21世紀的最重要的事
如果你想要用的
神經病
如果你想做麵包
不要動我
NVIDIA 揮達的執行長黃仁勳
在史丹佛演講的英文影片
是我最近在網路上面看到最精彩
而且最有啟發的一次演講
以下是特別為你製作的精華整理
場上場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場
拜託我們在一起工作上
接著再次接著再次
接著再接著再接接接接接
接著再接接接接接接
所以接著再接接
所以接著再接接接
接上去接接接接接接接接接接接接接接接接接接接接接接接接接接接接接接接接接接接接接接接接接接接接接接接接接接接接接接接接接接接接接接接接接接接接接接接接接接接接接接接接接接接接接接接接接接接接接接接接接接接接接接接接接接接接接接接接接接接接接接接接接接接接接接接接接接接接接接接接接接接接接接接接接接接接接接接接接接接接接接接接接接接接接接接接接接接接接接接接接接接接接接接接接接接接接接接接接接接接接接接接接接接接接接接接接接接接接接接接接接接接
你的 opening remarks,
it is smartest for me not to make any opening remarks
to avoid risking damaging all the good things you said.
But let's see, it's always good to have a pick-up line.
And mine was, do you want to see my homework?
And you're right, we're married still.
We have two beautiful kids, I have a perfect life,
two great puppies, and I love my job.
And she still enjoys my homework.
So in my lifetime I thought the biggest technical development,
technology breakthrough was the transistor.
Now I'm older than you.
And it was pretty fundamental.
But should I rethink, is AI now the biggest change in technology
that has occurred in the last 76 years?
To hint at my age.
Yeah, well first of all, the transistor
was obviously a great invention.
But what was the greatest capability
that enabled was software?
The ability for humans to express our ideas, algorithms,
in a repeatable way, computationally repeatable way,
was, is the breakthrough.
What have we done?
We dedicated our company in the last 30 years, 31 years,
to a new form of computing called accelerated computing.
The idea is that general purpose computing
is not ideal for every field of work.
And we said, why don't we invent a new way
of doing computation such that we can solve problems
that general purpose computing is ill-equipped at solving.
And what we have effectively done in a particular area,
a domain of computation that is algorithmic in nature,
that can be paralyzed, we've taken the computational cost
of computers to approximately zero.
So what happens when you are able to take the marginal cost
of something to approximately zero?
We enabled a new way of doing software
where it used to be written by humans,
we now can use computers to write the software.
Because the computational cost is approximately zero.
And so you might as well let the computer go off
and grind on just a massive amount of experience,
we call data, digital experience, human digital experience,
called data, and grind on it to find relationships and patterns.
that as a result represents human knowledge.
And that miracle happened about a decade and a half ago.
We saw it coming and we took the whole company
and we shaped our computer, which was already driving
the marginal cost of computing down to zero.
And we pushed it into this whole domain.
And as a result, in the last 10 years,
we reduced the cost of computing by one million times.
The cost of deep learning by one million times.
And a lot of people said to me, but Jensen,
if you reduce the cost of computing, your cost,
by a million times, then people buy less of it.
And it's exactly the opposite.
We saw that if we could reduce the marginal cost of computing down
to approximately zero, we might use it to do something insanely
amazing, large language models.
To literally extract all of digital human knowledge
from the internet and put it into a computer
and let it go figure out what the knowledge is.
That idea of scraping the entire internet
and putting it in one computer and let the computer figure out
what the program is, is an insane concept.
But you wouldn't ever consider doing it
unless the marginal cost of computing is zero.
And so we made that breakthrough.
And now we've enabled this new way of doing software.
Imagine, for all the people that are still new
to artificial intelligence, we figured out how to use a computer
to understand the meaning, not the pattern,
but the meaning of almost all digital knowledge.
And anything you can digitize, we can understand the meaning.
So let me give you an example.
Gene sequencing is digitizing genes.
But now with large language models, we can go understand,
go learn the meaning of that gene.
Amino acids, we digitized through mass spec.
We digitized amino acids.
Now we can understand from the amino acid sequence
without a whole lot of work with cryo-EMs and things like that.
We can go figure out what is the structure of the protein
and what it does.
What is this meaning?
We can also do that on a fairly large scale pretty soon.
We can understand what's the meaning of a cell.
A whole bunch of genes that are connected together.
And this is, from a computer's perspective, no different.
Then there's a whole page of words,
and you asked it to, what is the meaning of it?
Summarize, what did it say?
Summarize it for me.
What's the meaning?
This is no different than a hard, big, huge, long page of genes.
What's the meaning of that?
Big, long page of proteins.
And so we're on the cusp of all this.
This is the miracle of what happened.
And so I would, it's a long winded answer of saying, John,
that you're absolutely right, that AI, which was enabled by this form,
this new form of computing we call accelerated computing,
that took three decades to do, is probably the single greatest invention
of the computer, of the technology industry.
This will likely be the most important thing in the 21st century.
I take it that the GPU chip that is behind artificial intelligence right now is your H100,
and I know you're introducing an H200.
And I think I read that you plan to upgrade that each year.
And so could you think ahead five years, March 2029, you're introducing the H700.
Right.
What will it allow us to do that we can't do now?
I'll go backwards, but let me first say something about the chip that John just described.
As we say a chip, all of you in the audience probably, because you've seen the chip before,
you imagine there's a chip kind of like this. The chip that John just described weighs 70 pounds.
It consists of 35,000 parts. Eight of those parts came from TSMC.
That one chip replaces a data center of old CPUs like this into one computer.
The savings, because we compute so fast, the savings of that one computer is incredible,
and yet it's the most expensive computer the world's ever seen.
It's a quarter of a million dollars per chip.
We sell the world's first quarter million dollar chip.
But the system that it replaced, the cables alone cost more than the chip, this H100.
The cables of connecting all those old computers.
That's the incredible thing that we did.
We reinvented computing, and as a result, computing, marginal cost of computing went to zero.
That's what he just explained.
We took this entire data center, and we shrunk it into this one chip.
Well, this one chip is really, really great at trying to figure out this form of computation
that without getting weird on you guys, called deep learning.
It's really good at this thing called AI.
And so the way that this chip works, it works not just at the chip level,
but it works at the chip level, and the algorithm level, and the data center level.
It works together. It doesn't do all of its work by itself.
It works as a team.
And so you connect a whole bunch of these things together, and it works at networking as part of it.
And so when you look at one of our computers, it's a magnificent thing.
Only computer engineers would think it's magnificent, but it's magnificent.
It weighs a lot, miles and miles of cables, hundreds of miles of cables.
And the next one's soon coming as liquid cooled, and it's beautiful in a lot of ways.
And it computes at data center scales.
And together, what's going to happen in the next ten years, say John,
we'll increase the computational capability for deep learning by another million times.
And what happens when you do that? What happens when you do that?
Today, we kind of learn, and then we apply it. We go train, inference.
We learn, and we apply.
In the future, we'll have continuous learning.
We could decide whether whatever that continuous learning result will be deployed into, you know,
the world's applications or not, but the computer will watch videos and new text,
and from all the interactions, it's just continuously improving itself.
The learning process, and the training process, and the inference process,
and the deployment process, application process will just become one.
Well, that's exactly what we do.
You know, we don't have like between now and 7 o'clock in the morning,
I'm going to be doing my learning, and then after that I'll just be doing inference.
You're learning and inferencing all the time.
And that reinforcement learning loop will be continuous.
And that reinforcement learning will be grounded with real-world data that is being,
through interaction, as well as synthetically generated data that we're creating in real time.
So this computer will be imagining all the time. Does that make sense?
Just like, just as when you're learning, you take pieces of information, and you go,
from first principles it should work like this, and then we do the simulation,
the imagination in our brain, and that future imagined state, in a lot of ways,
manifests itself to us as reality.
And so your AI computer in the future will kind of do the same.
It'll do synthetic data generation, it'll do reinforcement learning,
it'll continue to be grounded by real-world experiences,
it'll imagine some things, it'll test it with real-world experience,
it'll be grounded by that, and that entire loop is just one giant loop.
That's what happens when you can compute for a million times cheaper than today.
And so as I'm saying this, notice what's at the core of it.
When you can drive the marginal cost of computing down to zero,
then there are many new ways of doing something you're willing to do.
This is no different than, I'm willing to go further places,
because the marginal cost of transportation has gone to zero.
I can fly from here to New York relatively cheaply.
If it would have taken a month, you know, I'll probably never go.
And so it's exactly the same in transportation, and just about everything that we do.
And so we're going to take the marginal cost of computing down to approximately zero.
As a result, we'll do a lot more computation.
That causes me, as you probably know, there have been some recent stories that NVIDIA will face more competition
in the inference market than it has in the training market.
But what you're saying is it's actually going to be one market, I think.
Can you comment about, you know, is there going to be a separate training chip market
and inference chip market, or it sounds like you're going to be continuously training
and switching to inference maybe within one chip, I don't know. Why don't you explain some more?
Well today, whenever you prompt an AI, it could be ChatGPT, or it could be CoPilot,
or it could be if you're using a ServiceNow platform, you're using Midjourney, using Firefly from Adobe.
Whenever you're prompting, it's doing inference.
You know, inference isn't right, so it's generating information for you.
Whenever you do that, what's behind it, 100% of them, is NVIDIA's GPUs.
And so NVIDIA's, most of the time you engage our platforms are when you're inferencing.
And so we're 100% of the world's inferencing today is NVIDIA.
Now is inferencing hard or easy?
A lot of people, the reason why people are picking on inference is when you look at training,
and you look at NVIDIA's system doing training, when you just look at it, you go,
that looks too hard. I'm not going to go do that. I'm a chip company. That doesn't look like a chip.
And so there's a natural, and you have to, in order for you to even prove that something works or not,
you're $2 billion into it. And you turn it on to realize it's not very effective,
you're $2 billion in two years into it. The risk of exploring something new is too high for the customers.
And so a lot of competitors tend to say, you know, we're not into training, we're into inference.
Inference is incredibly hard. Let's think about it for a second.
The response time of inference has to be really high, but this is the easy part.
That's the computer science part. The hard part of inference is the goal of somebody who's doing inference
is to engage a lot more users, to apply that software to a large installed base.
Inference is an installed base problem. This is no different than somebody who's writing an application on an iPhone.
The reason why they do so is because iPhone has such a large installed base, almost everyone has one.
And so if you wrote an application for that phone, it's going to have the benefit of,
it's going to be able to benefit everybody. Well, in the case of NVIDIA, our accelerated computing platform
is the only accelerated computing platform that's literally everywhere.
And because we've been working on it for so long, if you wrote an application for inference,
and you take that model and you deploy it on NVIDIA's architecture, it literally runs everywhere.
And so you can touch everybody, you can enable, have greater impact.
And so the problem with inference is actually installed base. And that takes enormous patience and years and years of success
and dedication to architecture compatibility, you know, so on and so forth.
You make completely state-of-the-art chips. Is it possible though that you'll face competition that claims to be good enough?
Not as good as NVIDIA, but good enough and much cheaper. Is that a threat?
Well, first of all, competition, we have more competition than anyone on the planet has competition.
Not only do we have competition from competitors, we have competition from our customers.
Yeah, that's true.
And I'm the only competitor to a customer, fully knowing they're about to design a chip to replace ours.
And I show them not only what my current chip is, I show them what my next chip is, and I show them what my chip after that is.
And so, and the reason for that is because, look, if you don't make an attempt at explaining why you're good at something,
they'll never get a chance to buy your products. And so we're a completely open book in working with just about everybody in the industry.
And the reason for that, our advantage is several. Our advantage, what we're about is several.
We're about several things. Whereas you can build a chip to be good at one particular algorithm.
Remember, computing is more than even transformers. There's an idea called transformers.
There's a whole bunch of species of transformers, and there are new transformers being invented as we speak.
And the number of different types of software is really quite rich.
And the reason for that is because software engineers love to create new things, innovation.
And we want that. What NVIDIA is good at is that our architecture, not only does it accelerate algorithms,
it's programmable, meaning that you can use it for, we're the only accelerator for SQL.
SQL came about in the 1960s, IBM, 1970s, in storage computing.
I mean, SQL is structured data as important as it gets.
300 zettabytes of data being created every couple of years, most of it is in SQL, structured databases.
And so we can accelerate that. We can accelerate quantum physics.
We can accelerate Schrodinger's equations. We can accelerate just about everything. Fluids, particles.
Lots and lots of code. And so what NVIDIA is good at is the general field of accelerated computing.
One of them is generative AI. And so for a data center that wants to have a lot of customers,
some of it in financial services, some of it in manufacturing, so on and so forth,
in the world of computing, we're a great standard. We're in every single cloud.
We're in every single computer company. And so our company's architecture has become a standard, if you will,
after some 30-some odd years. And so that's really our advantage.
If a customer can do something specifically that's more cost-effective, quite frankly, I'm even surprised by that.
And the reason for that is this. Remember, our chip is only part, think of, when you see computers these days,
it's not a computer like a laptop, it's a computer as a data center. And you have to operate it.
And so people who buy and sell chips think about the price of chips.
People who operate data centers think about the cost of operations.
Our time to deployment, our performance, our utilization, our flexibility across all these different applications,
in total, allows our operations cost. They call it total cost of operations, TCO.
Our TCO is so good that even when the competitor's chips are free, it's not cheap enough.
And that is our goal, to add so much value that the alternative is not about cost.
And so, of course, that takes a lot of hard work, and we have to keep innovating and things like that,
and we don't take anything for granted. But we have a lot of competitors.
As you know, but maybe not everybody in the audience knows, there's this term artificial general intelligence, which basically...
I was hoping not to sound competitive, but John asked a question that kind of triggered a competitive gene.
And I came across... I want to say, I want to apologize, I came across, you know, if you will, a little competitive.
I apologize for that. I could have probably done that more artfully. I will next time.
He surprised me with a competitive... I thought it was on an economic forum.
You know, just walking in here, I asked him, I'd sent some questions to his team.
And I said, did you look at the questions? He says, no, I didn't look at the questions, I want it to be spontaneous.
Besides, I might start thinking about it, and then that would be bad.
So we're just kind of winging it here, both of us.
So I was asking, when do you think, and of course, when do you think we will achieve artificial general intelligence,
the sort of human level intelligence? Is that 50 years away? Is it five years away? What's your opinion?
I'll give you a very specific answer. But first, let me just tell you a couple things about what's happening that's super exciting.
First, of course, we're training these models to be multimodality, meaning that we will learn from sounds,
we'll learn from words, we'll learn from vision, and we'll just watch TV and learn, so on and so forth.
Okay, just like all of us. And the reason why that's so important is because we want AI to be grounded.
Grounded not just by human values, which is what ChatGPT really innovated.
Remember, we had large language models before, but it wasn't until reinforcement learning human feedback,
that human feedback that grounds the AI to something that we feel good about, human values.
Okay? And now, could you imagine, now you have to generate images and videos and things like that.
How does the AI know that hands don't penetrate through, you know, podiums, that feet stand above the ground,
that when you step on water, you all fall into it? So you have to ground it on physics.
And so now the AI has to learn, by watching a lot of different examples, and ideally, mostly video,
that certain properties are obeyed in the world. Okay? It has to create what is called a world model.
So one, we have to understand multimodality. There's a whole bunch of other modalities,
like, as I mentioned before, genes, amino acids, and proteins, and cells, which leads to organs,
and, you know, so on and so forth. And so we would like to, multimodality.
Second is greater and greater reasoning capabilities. A lot of the things that we already do,
reasoning skills are encoded in common sense. You know, common sense is reasoning that we all kind of take for granted.
And so there are a lot of things in our knowledge in the internet that already encodes reasoning,
and models can learn that. But there's higher level reasoning capabilities. For example,
there's some questions that you answer right now when we're talking, I'm mostly doing generative AI.
I'm not spending a whole lot of time reasoning about the question. However, there are certain problems,
like for example, planning problems, where I'm going to, that's interesting. Let me think about that.
And I'm cycling in the back, and I'm coming up with multiple plans. I'm traversing a tree.
Maybe I'm going through my graph, and, you know, I'm pruning my tree saying, this doesn't make sense.
But this I'm going to play, and I simulate in my head, and maybe I do some calculations, and so on and so forth.
That long thinking, that long thinking, AI is not good at today. Everything that you prompted the chat GPT,
your response instantaneously. We would like to prompt something into chat GPT, give it a mission statement,
give it a problem, and for it to think a while. Isn't that right? And so, so that kind of system,
you know, what computer science calls system two thinking, or long thinking, or planning, those kind of things,
reasoning, reasoning and planning, those kind of problems, I think we're going to, we're working on those things.
And I think that we're going to see some breakthroughs. And so in the future, the way you interact with AI will be very different.
Some of it will be just, just give me a question, a question and answer. Some of it will say, here's a problem, go work on it for a while.
Okay, tell me tomorrow. And it does the largest amount of computation it can do by tomorrow.
You could also say, I'm going to give you this problem, you know, spend $1,000 on it, but don't spend more than that.
And it comes back with the best answer within the thousand, or you know, so on and so forth.
Okay, so that's, now AGI. The question on AGI is what's the definition?
Yeah, in fact, that's kind of the supreme question. Now, if you ask me, if you say, Jensen, AGI is a list of tests.
And remember, an engineer can only, an engineer knows that we've, you know, anybody in the, in that, you know,
prestigious organization that I'm now part of, knows for sure about engineers, is that you need to have a specification,
and you need to know what the definition of success is. You need to have a test.
Now, if I, if I gave an AI a lot of math tests, and reasoning tests, and history tests, and biology tests, and medical exams, and bar exams,
and, you know, SATs, and NCATs, and every single test that you can possibly imagine, you make that list of tests,
and you put it in front of, put it in front of the computer science industry, I'm guessing in five years' time,
we'll do well in every single one of them. And so, if your definition of AGI is that it passes human tests,
then I will tell you five years. If you tell me, but is it, if you asked it to me a little bit differently the way you asked it,
that AGI is going to be, have human intelligence. Well, I'm not exactly sure how to specify all of your intelligence yet,
and nobody does really, and therefore it's hard to achieve as an engineer. Does that make sense?
Okay, so, so the answer is we're not sure, and, and, but we're all endeavoring to make it, you know, better and better.
So, I'm going to ask two more questions, and I'm going to turn it over, because I think there's lots of good questions out there.
The first one I was going to ask about is, could you just dive a little deeper into what you see as AI's role in drug discovery?
The first role is to understand, understand the meaning of the digital information that we have.
Right now we have, we have all, as you know, we have, we have a whole lot of amino acids.
We can now, because of AlphaFold, understand the protein structure of many of them.
But the question is now, what's the meaning of that protein? What's the meaning of this protein? What does it function?
It would be great just that you can chat with GPT. As you guys know, there's, you can chat with a PDF.
You take a PDF file, doesn't matter what it is, my favorites are you take a PDF file of a, of a research paper, and you load it into chat GPT, and you start, just talking to it.
It's like talking to the researchers. Just, you know, just ask, what inspired this, this research? What problem does it solve?
You know, what was the breakthrough? What was the, what was the state of art before that? What were the, what were the novel ideas?
Just talk to it like a human, okay? In the future, when you take a protein, put it into chat GPT, just like PDF.
What are you for? What, what enzymes activate you? You know, what makes you happy?
For example, there'll be a whole, whole sequence of genes and you're gonna take, and it represents a cell, you're gonna put that cell in.
What are you for? What do you do? What are you good for? You know? What are your hopes and dreams?
And so, so that's, that's one of the most profound things we can do, is to understand the meaning of biology.
Does that make sense? If we can understand the meaning of biology, as you guys know, once we understand the meaning of almost any information that it's in the world of computer science,
in the world of computing, amazing engineers and amazing scientists know exactly what to do with it.
But that's the breakthrough. The multi-omic, multi-omic understanding of biology.
And so, that's, if I could, you know, deep and shallow answer to your, I think that's probably the single most profound thing that we can do.
Boy, Oregon State and Stanford are really proud of you.
So, if I could switch gears just a little bit and just say, Stanford has a lot of aspiring entrepreneurs, students that are entrepreneurs
and maybe they're computer science majors or engineering majors of some sort.
Please don't build GPUs.
What, what advice would you give them to improve their chances of success?
You know, one of my, one of, I think one of my great advantages is that I have very low expectations.
And, and, and I mean that.
Most of, most of the Stanford graduates have very high expectations.
And you, and you deserve to have, have high expectations because you came from a great school.
Um, you were very successful.
You're at top of your, top of your class.
Uh, obviously you were able to pay for tuition.
Um, and, and, uh, and then you're graduating from one of the finest institutions on the planet.
You're surrounded by other kids that are just incredible.
You should have very, you naturally have very high expectations.
Um, people with very high expectations have very low resilience.
And, unfortunately, resilience matters in success.
I don't know how to teach it to you except for I hope suffering happens to you.
And, and, uh, I, I was fortunate that I grew up with, with, with, you know, with my parents, um, uh, providing a condition for us to be successful on the one hand.
Um, but there were plenty of, plenty of opportunities for setbacks and suffering and, um, you know, and, and to, to this day I used the word, the phrase pain and suffering inside our company with great glee.
And the reason, and I mean that, you know, boy, this is going to cause a lot of pain and suffering.
And I mean that in a happy way.
Um, because, because you want to train, you want to refine the character of your company.
You want that, you want greatness out of them.
And greatness is not intelligence as you know.
Greatness comes from character and character isn't, isn't formed out of smart people.
It's formed out of people who suffered.
And, and so, so that's, that's kind of the, and so if I could, if I could wish upon you, I don't know how to do it.
But, you know, for all of you Stanford students, I, I wish upon you, you know, ample doses of pain and suffering.
I'm going to back out on my promise and ask you one more question.
How do you, you seem incredibly motivated and energetic, but how do you keep your employees motivated and energetic when they probably become richer than they ever expected to?
Yeah, I'm surrounded, I'm surrounded by 55 people.
My management team, so you know, my, my, my, my management team, my direct reports is 55 people.
I write no reviews for any of them.
I give them constant reviews.
I, and they provide the same to me.
I, my compensation for them, is the, the bottom right corner of Excel.
I just drag it down.
Literally, many of our executives are paid the same, exactly the dollar.
I know it's weird.
It works.
And, and I don't do one on ones with any of them, unless they need me.
Then I'll drop everything for them.
I never have meetings with them just alone.
And they never hear me say something to them that is only for them to know.
There's not one piece of information that I put, that I somehow secretly tell e-staff that I don't tell the rest of the company.
And so in that, in that way, our company was designed for agility, for information to be, to flow as quickly as possible, for people to be empowered by what they are able to do, not what they know.
And, and so that's the architecture of our company.
I don't remember your question, but, but, oh, oh, oh, oh, oh, oh, oh, oh, I got it.
I got it.
And the, the answer, the answer for that is my behavior.
Yeah.
It's, how do I celebrate success?
How do I celebrate failure?
How do I talk about success?
How do I talk about setbacks?
Every single thing that I'm looking for opportunities to instill every single day, I'm looking for opportunities to, to, to keep on instilling the culture of the company.
And what is important?
What's not important?
What's the definition of good?
How do you compare yourself to good?
How do you think about good?
How do you think about a journey?
How do you think about results?
All of that, all day long.
I have a couple questions.
What's the story about your leather jacket?
And the second, the second is, according to your projection and calculation, in five to ten years, how much more semiconductor manufacturing capacity is needed to support the growth of AI?
Okay.
I appreciate the two questions.
The, the, the first question is, this is what my wife bought for me and this is what I'm wearing.
And, and because I do, I do zero percent of my own shopping, uh, as soon as something that doesn't, as soon as she finds something that doesn't make me itch, because she knows, she's known me since I was 17 years old and she thinks that everything makes me itch.
And the way I say I don't like something is it makes me itch.
And so as soon as she finds me something that doesn't make me itch, if you look at my closet, the whole closet is a shirt.
Because she doesn't want to shop for me again.
And so, so that's why, uh, this is all she bought me and this is all I'm wearing.
And if I, if I don't like the answer, I can go shopping.
Otherwise I could wear it.
And it's good enough for me.
Here we go.
The second question on the, the forecast is actually very, this is very, I'm horrible at forecasting.
But I'm very good at first principle reasoning of the size of the opportunity.
And so let me first reason for you, um, uh, I have no idea how many fabs, but here's, here's the thing that I do know.
The way that we do computing today, the, the, the information was, was written by someone, created by someone.
Creative by someone, it's basically pre-recorded.
All the words, all the videos, all the sound, everything that we do is retrieval based.
It was pre-recorded.
Does that make sense?
As I say that every time you touch on a phone, remember somebody wrote that and stored it somewhere.
It was pre-recorded.
Okay.
Every modality that you know.
In the future, because we're going to have AIs, it understands the current circumstance and because it can, it's tapped into all of the world's, you know, latest news and things like, it's called retrieval based.
Okay.
And it understand your context, meaning it understood why you asked, what you're asking about.
When you and I ask about the economy, we probably are meeting very different things.
And for very different context.
And based on that, it can generate exactly the right information for you.
So in the future, it already understands context.
And most of computing will be generative.
And today, a hundred percent of content is pre-recorded.
If in the future, a hundred percent of content will be generative, the question is, how many, how does that change the shape of computing?
And so without torturing you anymore, I'll, I'll, that's how I reason through things.
How much more networking do we need?
More and less of that?
Do we need memory of this?
And the answer is we're going to need more fabs.
However, remember that we're also improving the algorithms and the processing of it tremendously over time.
It's not as if the efficiency of computing is what it is today and therefore the demand is this much.
In the meantime, I'm improving computing by a million times every 10 years while demand is going up by a trillion times.
And that has to offset each other.
Does that make sense?
And then there's technology diffusion and so on and so forth.
That's just a matter of time.
But it doesn't change the fact that one day all of the computers in the world will be changed 100%.
Every single data center will be, all of those general purpose computing data centers, a hundred percent of the trillion dollars worth of infrastructure will be completely changed.
And then there'll be new infrastructure built on, even on top of that.
Okay, next question right here, Ben.
And then over here to Randy.
So yeah.
Thanks for coming today.
So recently you said that you encourage students not to learn how to code.
Yeah.
And if that's the case, it means one of maybe a few things.
But do you think the world starts to look like from a company formation and entrepreneurship perspective that it goes towards many, many more companies that are created?
Or do you think it's consolidation to just a number of the big players?
Yeah.
So first of all, I said it so poorly that you repeat it back poorly.
If you would like to code, for God's sakes, code.
Okay?
If you want to make omelets, make omelets.
I'm not, coding has, coding is a reasoning process.
It's good.
Is it going to guarantee you a job?
No, not even a little bit.
The number of coders in the world surely will continue to be important.
And we, NVIDIA needs coders.
However, in the future, the way you interact with the computer is not going to be C++ mostly.
For some of us, that's true.
For some of us, that's, but for you, you know, why program in Python?
So weird.
In the future, you'll tell the computer what you want.
And the computer will, you say, hi, I would like you to come up with a build plan with all of the suppliers and build material for a forecast that we have for you.
And based on all the equipment, all the necessary components, you're coming up with a build plan.
Okay?
And then if you don't like that, you just write me a Python program that I can modify of that build plan.
And so, remember, the first time I talked to the computer, I'm just speaking in plain English.
The second time, so English, by the way, human, is the best programming language of the future.
How you talk to a computer, how do you prompt it, how do you prompt it, it's called prompt engineering.
How do you interact with people, how do you interact with computers, how do you make a computer do what you want it to do,
how do you fine tune the instructions with that computer, that's called prompt engineering.
There's an artistry to that.
Okay?
So, for example, most people are surprised by this, but it's not surprising to me, but it's surprising.
For example, you ask the journey to generate an image of a puppy on a surfboard in Hawaii at sunset.
Okay?
And then it generates one.
And you go, and you say, oh, more cute.
Make it more cute.
And it comes back, it's more cute.
And you go, no, no, cuter than that.
And it comes back, why is it that software would do that?
There's a structural reason why it does that.
But for example, you need to know that that capability exists in a computer in the future.
Isn't that right?
If you don't like the answer the first time, you can fine tune it and get it to within the context that you can make it, give you better results.
And once you eat, you can even ask it to write the program altogether to generate that result in the future.
And so my point is that programming has changed in a way that is probably less valuable.
On the other hand, I will tell you this.
That because of artificial intelligence, we have closed the technology divide of humanity.
Today, about 10 million people are gainfully employed because we know how to program computers.
Which leaves the other 8 billion behind.
That's not true in the future.
We all can program computers.
Does that make sense?
You all know how to prompt a computer to make it do things.
And all you do is look at YouTube.
And look at all the people who are using prompt engineering, all the kids, you know, who are making it do amazing things.
They don't know how to program.
They're just talking to ChatGPT.
They just know that if I tell it to do this, it'll do that, you know.
And so it's no different than interacting with people in the future.
That's the great contribution the computer science industry has made to the world.
We've closed the technology divide.
That's inspiring.
Okay, over here.
We've got Randy with a question right over here.
Thank you very much.
I'm just wondering about, do you think very much about geopolitical risk?
And how do you see it impacting your industry if you do?
Geopolitical risk, we are almost the poster child of geopolitical risk.
And the reason for that is because we make a very important instrument for artificial intelligence.
And artificial intelligence, as John and I were talking about earlier, is the defining technology of this time.
And so the United States has every right to determine that this instrument should be limited to countries that it determines that it should be limited with.
And so the United States has that right and they exercise that right.
And your question has to do with what is the implication to us?
First of all, we just have to understand these policies and we have to stay agile so that we can comply with the policies.
Number one.
On the one hand, it limits our opportunity in some places and it opens up opportunities in others.
One of the things that has happened in the last, I would say, maybe even six to nine months, is the awakening of every single country, every single society.
The awakening that they have to control their own digital intelligence.
That India can't outsource its data so that some country transforms that digital data into India's intelligence and imports that intelligence back to India.
That awakening, that sovereign AI that you have to dedicate yourself to control your sovereign AI, your sovereign intelligence, protect your language, protect your culture for your own industries.
That awakening, I think, happened in the last six, nine months.
The first part was, we have to be mindful about safety.
And the second part was, hold on a second, we all have to do this.
And so every single country from India, Canada is doing this, the UK, France, Japan, Singapore, Malaysia, the list goes on.
Just about every single country now realize that they have to invest in their own sovereign AI.
So geopolitics, in the one hand, limited opportunities, but it created just enormous opportunities elsewhere.
And so, hard to say.
Okay, so I think we have multiple hands, but I have time for one more question.
I am going to go right here. You were further on the ground.
Now remember, the last question has all, big pressure.
You guys agree with that?
Can we all agree?
The person who asked the last question, don't leave us all depressed.
Don't trigger me, please. That's all I'm saying. I'm just kidding.
I'm going to invoke your commandment to have low expectations at this juncture.
You mentioned you're competing with your customers, and I'm wondering, given the advantages that you have, why they're doing that.
And I'm wondering if in the future you see yourself building more customized solutions for customers of a certain scale, as opposed to the solutions that you have now, which are more horizontal.
So are we willing to customize the answer to yes?
Now, why is it that the bar is relatively high?
The reason why the bar is high is because each generation of our platform, first of all, there's a GPU, there's a CPU, there's a networking processor.
There are two types of switches. I just build five chips for one generation. People think there's one chip, but there's five different chips.
Each one of those chips are hundreds and hundreds of millions of dollars to do.
Just hitting launch, which is tape out for us, launching a rocket is several hundred million dollars each time.
Okay? I've got five of them per generation.
Then you've got to put them into a system. And then you've got to put, you know, you've got networking stuff, you've got transceiver stuff, you've got optic stuff, you've got a mountain of software to do.
It takes a lot of software to run a computer as big as this room.
And so all of that is complicated. If the customization is so different, then you have to repeat the entire R&D.
However, if the customization leverages everything and adds something to it, then it makes a great deal of sense.
Maybe it's a proprietary security system. Maybe it's a confidential computing system. Maybe it's a new way of doing numerical processing that could be extended.
We're very open minded to that. And our customers know that I'm willing to do all that and recognize that if you change it too far,
If you change it too far, you've basically reset and you've squandered, you know, the nearly 100 billion dollars that's taken us to get here to redo from scratch and so they want to leverage our ecosystem to the extent that that will be done, I'm very open to it and they know that.
Yeah and they know and they know that.
下面的连结到LINE跟Discord群组
跟努力的大家一起讨论
我们在OKXPN派网呢
跟其他的大交易所都帮大家争取到了
最高8折20% OFF的交易手续费减免
用下面的连结注册呢
你的交易成本就更低了
也欢迎告诉我你接下来想要看什么
我们在币圈继续努力
下次见 拜拜
请不吝点赞 订阅 转发 打赏支持明镜与点点栏目